I'm dr. John Verve a key from the
University of Toronto I teach in the
cognitive psychology department the
cognitive science program and the
Buddhism psychology and mental health
program I teach a course on the science
of mindfulness meditation I teach a
course on cultivating consciousness
where I teach meditation and
contemplative practices and I also teach
extracurricular courses here on
meditation on contemplation and on touch
each one I'd like to introduce you to
the the basics of mindfulness meditation
especially from the past no tradition
and the core of mindfulness meditation
is finding your Center and that's a sort
of which become a cliche thing to say
and what I want to do is make that a
little bit more precise and powerful and
useful for you by talking about three
centers you're going to find the first
Center you're going to find is the
relationship between mind and body so
this is the Buddhist the central
Buddhist metaphor that in mindfulness
practice we're learning to befriend
ourselves we're trying to take the
relationship towards a friend right but
take that relationship towards ourselves
and one of the way we do that is we try
to get the body in mind working together
using the mind to train the body and the
body to train the mind and one of the
ways we can do that is by adopting some
basic principles of posture so what I
want to do right in my posture is I want
to find my Center I don't want to sort
of just calculate because I don't want
to hold myself rigid because if I hold
myself rigid that makes me tense and
that triggers the wrong kinds of mental
states if I but if I let myself go limp
then I'm cutting off a lot of my oxygen
I'm not breathing properly i got this
sort of shallow chest breathing and that
also is associated with anxiety
restlessness of mind so what I want is I
want to move off the back of my chair
and what I'm going to do is take you
through this exercise you do so you
close your eyes and you're going to pay
attention to your sensations of balance
you're going to move forward and feel
off balance move backwards and feel off
balance and then slowly changing each
one home in to where you feel right
centered on this axis front to back then
you're going to repeat it you're going
to go side to side again paying
attention to the sensations of being off
balance slowly homing in to where you
feel centered
way then it's important to do the head
independently because one of the most
common mistakes and novice meditators is
they let their head roll forward when
they're meditating and this is bad for a
few reasons first it upsets your center
of balance and it will put a strain on
your neck which will tend to cause
headaches secondly it tends to restrict
your air again so you're doing the
shallow breathing again which tends to
trigger restlessness and finally your
sort of signal inning to your brain that
you're falling asleep which is not what
we want in meditation in meditation
we're trying to get in between a
restless mind a mind running around but
on mine that's going foggy and falling
asleep we want to calm but very clear
mind so we want to do the exercise also
with the head back to front side to side
once you've found your Center once
you've sent your Center sink into it
relax your structure as much as you can
open your stomach muscles open your
chest place your hands where they're
conducive to adding to the stability
right but what you want to do is you
want to trust your structure as much as
you can so you want to sink into your
Center and then once you're sinking into
your Center you want to save her your
Center what does it feel like in your
mind and body to be centered you're
trying to create a felt memory so you
can get back to this place again and
again more and more readily so what
you're going to do first is you're going
to sit you're going to find your Center
you're going to sense your Center you're
going to sink into your Center then
you're going to savor your Center then
the next thing you're going to do is
you're going to send your attention many
of you know that meditation involves
sort of focusing your attention but
there's more to that right in meditation
we're not just focusing our attention so
what we're going to do is we're going to
learn to step back and look at our mind
rather than looking through it in our
day-to-day lives we don't pay much
attention to our minds we pay a lot of
attention through our minds to the world
so I'm going to use an analogy for that
most of the time i'm looking through my
glasses i'm not i'm not actually looking
at them but periodically especially if
there's something distorting my vision I
need to step back and look at my glasses
and that's what I want to practice doing
and mindfulness I want to practice
stepping back and looking
the mind rather than automatically
looking through it the way we do this is
to look at what we have we normally
reach out to the world with our mind
through our sensations normally we don't
pay attention to our sensations we pay
attention through them so what we're
going to do is focus this area is called
aired on TN and we're going to focus to
the sensations that are being created by
our breathing now be careful don't force
your breathing just let let your be
anything remain natural so what you want
to do is as you're breathing in you're
going to pay attention to the sensations
of your abdomen expanding and you're
going to silently say to yourself in and
feel all the sensations here that are
being generated and then and then as
you're naturally breathing out you're
going to silently be saying to yourself
out and be pay attention to all the
sensations that are being generated now
what will happen is that automatic
tendency that your mind has to start
looking at the world will take over and
you'll be distracted you'll start
thinking about your laundry you'll be
listening to somebody in the hallway
you're both be imagining some seen what
we want to do is again step back and
look at rather than looking through it
now what do I mean by that what I mean
is I'm not going to get involved with
what I'm thinking about I'm instead I'm
going to step back and label the process
that process going on in my mind with an
ING word like thinking imagining
listening and then I'm going to return
my attention back to the breath
following the breath at the dawn TN and
that brings me to the third thing I'm
going to Center I'm going to Center my
attitude the attitude i'm taking towards
this practice now jack kornfield has a
wonderful analogy for this he says it's
like training your puppy dog to stay he
said so imagine you're training your
puppy dog to stay and you put your puppy
dog down here and the puppy dog
inevitably is going to right move the
first thing you have to do is note where
it goes but your attitude is also
important if I bring the puppy dog you
know stay and I have this really
punitive attitude and I'm judging and
I'm harsh right on i'm punishing i'm
training the puppy dog to resist me to
fear me to fight me I'm not pro
friending myself anymore now I'm
training the mind to be closed off right
to me and I'm trying I'm doing exactly
the opposite i want but
right if I do the opposite right and I
just oh there goes the puppy dog and I
don't oh well how wonder right if I'm
just lacks today is equal and easy the
puppy dog also won't be trained what I
need to do is write to be persistent you
know stay stay but I need to not be
punitive so this part of your mind that
jumps around in the Buddhist literature
it's called your monkey mind because
it's like a monkey leaping your own
chattering as it leaps around the trees
and a way of thinking about this is we
don't want to feed our monkey mind we
don't want to just indulge it and let it
run wild but on the other hand we don't
want to fight our monkey mind we want
we're not trying to like punish it and
you know be harsh to it we're trying to
Center our attitude between fighting and
feeding our monkey mind so you're
sitting I'm going to sit to meditate
you're going to do the three centers
you're going to sense your the center
between mind and body and savor it right
right sink into it you're going to then
Center your mind by stepping back and
looking at your sensations rather than
looking through them stepping back and
labeling the distracting process rather
than looking through it at what's its
pointing your attention towards and
you're also going to send your Center
your attitude by how you return to the
breath persistent but not punitive
neither like feeding or fighting your
monkey mind and that's how you begin to
do mindfulness meditation